Guide to the Alva I. Cox Jr. Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- National Council of the Churches of Christ in the U.S.A. (NCC), Series II
  - Social Awareness / Social Justice Issues
    - "Mississippi Old/Rural"; black and white photographs of people in rural Mississippi. (slide carousel) (Box 121)
    - "NCC"; This tape discusses the NCC's involvement in child advocacy, issues of racism, and helping low-income families such as migrant workers in Nebraska. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington. "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; Raw footage from this conference. (VHS - VTC): 4 volumes), Oct. 18, 1990 (Box 36)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 1 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002098994875)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 2 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 34, Item barcode 39002098994883)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 3 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994909)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 4 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994917)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 5 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994925)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 6 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994933)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 7 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994941)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 8 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994958)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 9 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 35, Item barcode 39002098994966)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 10 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 36, Item barcode 39002098994974)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 11 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 36, Item barcode 39002098994982)
    - "NCC Drug Consultation Seminar"; raw footage from NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington Part 12 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 36, Item barcode 39002098994990)
    - NCC Substance Abuse / Narcotics Consultation in Washington"Drug Consultation Selects"; Selections from the NCC Narcotics Conference. (U-matic S) (Box 96)
    - "Substance Abuse--Washington"; This is the final version of the film about the NCC Substance Abuse Consultation. (Beta Master) (Box 37)
    - "Cecil Murray Speech"; A speech from the Substance Abuse Consultation. (Beta Master), No date; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002098995005)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." Part 1: Welcome and Intro- Diane Porter; The Pattern of Racism- Reverend Sam Mann (VHS), Oct. 30 -- Nov. 2, 1987; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002098995013)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." Part 2, 1987; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002098995021)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." Part 3, 1987; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002129368743)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." Part 4, 1987; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002129368750)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." Part 6: Reparations, 1987; 1 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002129368768)
    - "NCC-- on Racism"; Raw footage of the conference "Reframing the Dialogue on Racism." (Betacam SP: 5 volumes) (Box 71–72)
- NCC and WCC, Series III
  - About NCC and WCC
    - "The Gospel According to Whom" (60 Minutes, CBS); This is a recording made from television. The segment deals with how funds of the NCC and WCC are being used. There are concerns about the NCC being "radically left," as well as accusations that the NCC is using funds to support Communism and Communistic propaganda. There are also accusations that funds from the WCC are being used to support guerrillas in Africa. (VHS), Jan. 1983 (Box 154)
    - "Unity and Reconciliation" (VHS: 2 copies one a VTC), Nov. 3, 1991 (Box 37–38)
      This film focuses on the work of the NCC and WCC to unify and help with reconciliation. An example of efforts at reconciliation are in the "Pilgrimage for Peace," where Christian leaders from the U.S. travel to the Middle East on a mission of peace to try and end the Gulf War. Then the film shifts focus to unity within the church when Rev. Billy Graham speaks with the NCC. This focus on unity and reconciliation continues when the WCC visits the Aborigines of Australia. Finally, the film relates issues of feminism and feminist theology to unity and reconciliation, concluding with the installation of Rev. Joan Campbell as General Secretary of the NCC.
    - "Unity and Reconciliation" (U-matic: 2 copies), 1991 (Box 70, Box 73, Item barcode 39002098996029)
    - "Unity and Reconciliation" (D-2 Composite Digital Master) (Box 73)
    - "Visitation to Vatican" (Original); Members of the NCC and WCC visit the Pope at the Vatican. (VHS: 2 copies), 1989 (Box 154, Box 156)
    - "Visitation to Vatican" (U-matic), 1989; 1 (Box 73, Item barcode 39002098996011)
  - Action and Aid from the NCC and WCC
    - "A Legacy to Share: From Governing Board to General Board"; This film is about various ways that the NCC and WCC are involved in social justice issues. (VHS: 2 copies), May 15, 1990 (Box 38)
    - "A Legacy to Share: From Governing Board to General Board" (Beta) (Box 38)
    - "A Legacy to Share: From Governing Board to General Board" (U-matic), 1991; 1 (Box 74, Item barcode 39002098996037)
    - "Racism is a Violation of Human Rights" (The NCC-WCC Press Conference); This program consists of excerpts from various speeches at this conference Washington, D.C.(VHS), Oct. 19, 1994; 1 (Box 38, Item barcode 39002098995039)
- World Council of Churches (WCC), Series IV
  - WCC Conferences
    - "Celebrations: Amsterdam--WCC, (etc.)" (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 39, Item barcode 39002098995047)
    - "Come Holy Spirit / Hope and Challenge" (WCC Australia) (VHS), 1991; 1 (Box 39, Item barcode 39002098995070)
      This film shows a brief history of the WCC, followed by a look into the process of and activities at the assembly in Australia.
    - "The Face of All the Earth"; This film is also about the WCC conference in Australia, yet it is different than that of the film "Come Holy Spirit." (VHS), 1991 (Box 39)
    - "The Face of All the Earth" (Beta), 1991; 1 (Box 72, Item barcode 39002098995997)
- Church World Services (CWS), Series V
  - About the CWS
    - "Share the Struggle, Share the Joy" (VHS), June 6 and 29, 1987 (Box 39)
      This film celebrating the 40th anniversary of Church World Service is about receiving help from and giving help to farmers. U.S. farms provide CWS with food for countries in need. Later, as U.S. farms go through drought, CWS provides aid for them, too.
    - "Share the Struggle, Share the Joy" (U-matic), 1987; 1 (Box 74, Item barcode 39002098996052)
    - "CWS 40th Anniversary"; Raw footage of the 40th anniversary of CWS. (Beta: 5 volumes) (Box 40)
  - The CWS in Action
    - "Armenia Earthquake Appeal" (VHS), Dec. 1988; 1 (Box 39, Item barcode 39002098995054)
      This program is about aid provided by CWS for the victims of the Armenia earthquake. It shows how the CWS works in this kind of disaster, such as by shipping medical supplies and blankets to Armenia.
    - "CWS Africa Emergency"; This film is about aid provided by CWS to Ethiopia, Senegal, and Somalia. (VHS), June 27, 1985; 1 (Box 39, Item barcode 39002098995062)
    - "Gewaha Medical Center"; This program is about an African medical center run by CWS, whose members help with undernourished and malnourished children. The program is short. (VHS) (Box 40)
    - "Signs of Change" (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 40, Item barcode 39002098995088)
      This program is about help provided by CWS for the drought in Africa. CWS provided crop seeds, built water pumps for wells using local materials, and trained locals how to build and maintain their new water equipment.
    - "Somalia Appeal--Africa Drought Appeal"; This 7-minute video consists of two commercials appealing for donations. The first shows CWS providing food in Somalia. The second shows water conservation and agricultural help provided by CWS. (VHS), 1992 (Box 41)
- The United Methodist Church, Series VI
  - Liturgy and Ministry
    - "The Frontier is the Spirit"; This film is about the ministry of the United Methodist Church in Alaska. (VHS), Oct. 17, 1986; 1 (Box 41, Item barcode 39002098995096)
    - "A.C.S."; Raw footage used in "The Frontier is the Spirit," containing exterior shots, interviews, mountain climbing, native dances, etc. (U-matic S: 25 volumes), July and Aug., 1986 (Box 97–104)
    - "The Hardest Job in the World"; Rev. Glen "Tex" Evans speaks to Methodist ministers about the privilege of being a pastor (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "3 Ready"; This tape is from a meeting about how the UMC can help Native Alaskans, farmers, etc. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "Theological Task Force USA Consultations"; This tape discusses the Methodist theological tradition, the actions and organization of each continent's consultation. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
  - Conferences
    - "An Oasis of Hope" (Gulfside--United Methodist Assembly); This is about a facility, "Gulfside," given to the UMC by African-American Methodists as a retreat setting. (VHS) (Box 41)
    - "An Oasis of Hope" (Gulfside--United Methodist Assembly); This is about a facility, "Gulfside," given to the UMC by African-American Methodists as a retreat setting.(U-matic), No date; 1 (Box 74, Item barcode 39002098996045)
    - "New Era Initiative (with Bishop Forrest Stith)"; New York Annual Conference, United Methodist Church. Final version (VHS: 2 copies), Nov. 28, 1994; 2 (Box 41, Item barcode 39002098995104)
    - "New Era Initiative (with Bishop Forrest Stith)"; New York Annual Conference, United Methodist Church. Final version (D-2 Edited Master) (Box 104)
    - "New Era Initiative (with Bishop Forrest Stith)"; New York Annual Conference, United Methodist Church. Final version Resource Materials (Beta: 16 volumes (two of these are titled "La Ressurrection) (Box 42–44)
    - "New Era Initiative (with Bishop Forrest Stith)"; New York Annual Conference, United Methodist Church. Final version Resource Materials (VHS NYAC Reel 1-4 [Window Dubs Bronx])., Sep. 1994 (Box 41)
    - "Orthodox and Wesleyan Spirituality"; This program is from a consultation of Orthodox and Methodist Churches. (9 VHS: 2 volumes), April 14 and May 11, 1999; 9 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002098995112)
    - "Response / New World Outlook"; This film is about Response, the magazine for United Methodist women. (VHS), April 14, 1986 (Box 41)
    - "Response / New World Outlook" (U-matic) (Box 75)
    - "United Methodist Church, Canton/Warren, OH"; Raw footage used in "Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice." (U-matic S: 6 volumes), May 17-18, 1987 (Box 104–106)
    - "United Methodist Church, Canton/Warren, OH"; Raw footage used in "Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice." (Beta: 16 volumes) (Box 44–48)
    - Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice (U-matic), 1987; 1 (Box 75, Item barcode 39002098996078)
  - Programs and Activities
    - "Africa"; This is a rough draft of "Africa Church Growth and Development," which is about the UMC in Africa. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "Sam Dhlamini--Catch the Spirit"; Sam Dhlamini is an artist and teacher in South Africa. The UMC in New Hampshire has a program that brings individuals like Sam from South Africa to the U.S. as students, and then returns them to South Africa to help educate others. Final version (VHS: 2 copies) (Box 154, Box 156)
    - "Sam Dhlamini--Catch the Spirit" Final version (U-matic S SP Dubmaster), No date; 1 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002098996201)
    - "Sam Dhlamini--Catch the Spirit" Resource materials (U-matic S: 5 volumes) (Box 111)
    - "The Challenge of Change" Final version (VHS), 1985; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002098995120)
      This film is aimed at promoting the expansion of programs within the United Methodist Church in New Jersey. As the population continues to increase in numbers and diversity, new and changing methods of ministry need to be implemented. Programs such as those aimed at teaching oneself and others about one's culture are an example of such new ministry presented by this "challenge of change."
    - "The Challenge of Change" Final verson (16 mm) (Box OV8)
    - "The Challenge of Change" Resource materials (U-matic S: 18 volumes), April 18-29, 1985 (Box 106–109)
    - "Holy Boldness / Shalom Convocation" (VHS), March 22, 1999 (Box 48)
      In response to the Los Angeles riots, the UMC created both "shalom zones" and the Holy Boldness Program. Together, these have seven goals: 1) Urban Theology, 2) Evangelism and congregational development, 3) Eradicating racism and other forms of oppression, 4) Strengthening multicultural relationships, 5) Community economic development, 6) Leadership development, 7) Wholeness, healing, and health.
    - "Holy Boldness / Shalom Convocation" (Beta ), 1999; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002098995138)
    - "Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice"; This film consists of stories of faith and praise within the East Ohio Conference of the United Methodist Church. These stories address the results and goals for financial resources within the conference. Final version (VHS), Sep. 8, 1986 (Box 48)
    - "Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice" Final version (U-matic) (Box 75)
    - "Rejoice, Again I Say Rejoice" Resource materials (U-matic S: 2 volumes - "East Ohio") (Box 104)
    - "To Do Justice: United Methodist Women" (VHS), Nov. 18, 1997; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002098995146)
      This film focuses on United Methodist women becoming involved in issues of social justice. The film first examines the history of Methodists and Methodist women being active in social justice issues, and then continues the examination with current activities of Methodist women.
    - "To Do Justice: United Methodist Women" (VHS - 2nd copy), 1997 (Box 49)
- Church Burnings, Series VII
  - "Burned in Hate--Rebuilt in Love" (New Hope Baptist Church--Seattle, WA) (VHS: 2 copies), Sep. 24, 1999 (Box 125)
    This program is about the burning of the New Hope Baptist Church in the mid-1990's. The official explanation of the cause of the fire is that it was an accident due to a faulty electrical box, but members of the congregation believe it was caused by people who had problems with the social activeness of this church, such as having reached an understanding with the Jewish community. However, members of the community help to rebuild this church.
  - "Burned in Hate--Rebuilt in Love" (New Hope Baptist Church - Seattle, WA) (Betacam S Master), 1999; 1 (Box 125, Item barcode 39002098996318)
  - "The Churches Are Burning"; This film is about the burnings of African-American churches in the 1990's, as well as the response of the NCC (of which all these burned churches were members). Final version (VHS), 1996; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002098995153)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" Resource materials (VHS: 13 volumes) (Box 49–50)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Shiloh - Humbold (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 51, Item barcode 39002098995187)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 1 (Beta), No date (Box 51, Item barcode 39002098995179)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 2 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995203)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 3 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995211)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 4 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995229)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 5 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995237)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 6 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995245)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Seattle, tape 7 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995252)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: Arkansas churches (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002098995195)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 1 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995260)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 2 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995278)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 3 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995286)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 4 (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995294)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 5A (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995302)
  - "The Churches Are Burning" resource materials: South Carolina, tape 5B (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002098995310)
  - "Congressional Hearing--Tape 1"; Black Church Burning; testimony to Black Caucus (VHS), 1996; 1 (Box 50, Item barcode 39002098995161)
  - "#13 TC"; Raw footage of an interview with Rev. Willy Coleman about his church being burned down in 1996. (VHS) (Box 51)
  - "Tape #2 NCC--Bombing of Black Churches"; Raw footage of the remains of a burned church from the mid-90's. (Beta) (Box 54)
  - "Burned Churches" (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 54, Item barcode 39002098995336)
    This is a Channel 1 News program (a teen news program). In it is a story about President Clinton's summit on volunteerism. The next story is about a militia standoff in Texas (after the incident in Waco). The final segment is about a volunteer helping rebuild burned churches.
  - "The Rebuilding of St. Mark's dub"; This film is about the rebuilding of St. Mark's Church after the church burnings of the 1990's. (VHS: 2 copies) (Box 153–154)
  - "The Rebuilding of St. Mark's Missionary Baptist Church, Chelford, Arkansas" (Beta), ca. 1997; 1 (Box 54, Item barcode 39002098995344)
  - "Workers Rebuild Churches" (The Ehrhardt Group International Paper); Raw footage of the rebuilding of a church (Beta) (Box 55)
- Yale, Series VIII
  - "#1 Yale Divinity"; Raw footage of Rev. James Forbes giving the Beecher Lecture at Marquand Chapel, Yale Divinity School. (VHS: 2 copies), March 31, 1986 (Box 153–154)
  - "#1 Yale Divinity" (U-matic) (Box 113)
  - "#4 Trio Yale Divinity"; A trio singing in Marquand Chapel. (VHS: 2 copies), April 2, 1986 (Box 153–154)
  - "#4 Trio Yale Divinity" (U-matic S), 1986; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002098996268)
- Social Awareness / Social Justice, Series IX
  - Societal Issues
    - "Beyond the News--Racism" (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 55, Item barcode 39002129368776)
      This program demonstrates how everyday life is orientated and privileged for Caucasians, such as standards of beauty found in magazines.
    - "Crime Victims: You Can Help" (VHS) (Box 55)
      This film addresses the consequences faced by victims of crime that are not fully realized by the justice system, nor insurance companies. To help deal with these consequences, communities should create a crime victim witness assistance program. Such a program tries to assist in everything from physical, to mental, to emotional, to economic needs of victims.
    - "Crime Victims: You Can Help" (U-matic), No date; 1 (Box 75, Item barcode 39002098996060)
    - "Good Sam."; Interview about the Good Samaritan Agency. (audio cassette) (Box 115)
    - "Inner City Entrepreneurial Training"; This is a program about economic empowerment of African-Americans in Seattle. (VHS Dub from TV) (Box 55)
    - "Inner City Entrepreneurial Training" (Beta Master) (Box 55)
    - "Making the Dream Come True: Project Equality"; This film is about Project Equality, a program that seeks equal rights and opportunities for women and minorities, especially in the workplace. (VHS), March 31, 1986 (Box 55)
    - "Making the Dream Come True: Project Equality" (U-matic), 1986; 1 (Box 76, Item barcode 39002098996094)
    - "Project Equality 30th Anniversary"; This is the film of the conference to celebrate that 30 years ago the Catholic Church began Project Equality, which seeks better opportunities for minorities and women. Final version (VHS), April 26-27, 1995 (Box 55)
    - "Project Equality 30th Anniversary" Resource materials (Box 55–56)
    - Project Equality 30th Anniversary; Breaking the Glass Ceiling; Achieving Diversity in the Workplace (Beta), 1995; 1 (Box 77, Item barcode 39002098996110)
    - Project Equality 30th Anniversary; Rev. Emanuel Clear, Richard Thieme addresses, 1995; 1 (Box 77, Item barcode 39002098996128)
    - "Project Equality 30th Anniversary" (Hi8 Metal-P: 4 volumes) (Box 127)
    - "Project Equality 30th Anniversary" (Beta: 16 volumes) (Box 56–58)
    - "See Jane Run" (VHS) (Box 58)
      This film is a 50 minute three-part film drama about a 13 year-old girl troubled by family problems and difficulties in school, who feels driven to run away from home and gradually falls into deeper trouble with the law. It is the story, too, of missed opportunities on the part of the school, the juvenile justice system and the community-at-large which because of a lack of viable alternatives and sensitive response, fail to meet the needs of Jane and her family.
    - "See Jane Run" (16 mm: 2 copies) (Box OV7)
    - "See Jane Run" (U-matic), No date; 1 (Box 76, Item barcode 39002098996102)
  - Issues in the U.S.A.
    - "Albuquerque: Rough Cut"; Raw footage of exterior shots and interviews about environmental problems in Albuquerque caused by plants which contaminate the water. (U-matic S) (Box 109)
    - "Chicken Ranch"; This film is about a legal brothel in Nevada. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002098995351)
    - "Dixiana--'Spirit of the Land'" (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002098995369)
      This is a musical thank-you from the South for being helped out by other states during a drought: "...and to the farmers, truckers, and companies across America who have shared the 'Spirit of the Land' with our Southern farmers, God bless you..."
    - "Early Days Ago: The Alaska Native Struggle to Retain Their Land"; This is one of the films commissioned to be made in response to the Land Claim Settlement in Alaska. (VHS) (Box 59)
    - "Early Days Ago: The Alaska Native Struggle to Retain Their Land" (16mm) (Box OV8)
    - "Early Days Ago: The Alaska Native Struggle to Retain Their Land" (U-matic: 3 copies), No date; 3 (Box 76, Item barcode 39002098996086, Box 78)
    - "On Our Own: Opportunities for Natives after Land Claim Settlement"; This is one of the films commissioned to be made in response to the Land Claim Settlement in Alaska. (VHS) (Box 59)
    - "On Our Own: Opportunities for Natives after Land Claim Settlement" (16mm) (Box OV8)
    - "On Our Own: Opportunities for Natives after Land Claim Settlement" (U-matic: 4 copies), No date; 4 (Box 78, Box 79, Item barcode 39002098996136)